<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://shannonwu.github.io</id>
    <title>空山夜语</title>
    <updated>2020-02-12T21:49:51.490Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://shannonwu.github.io"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://shannonwu.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>空山不见人，但闻人语响。</subtitle>
    <logo>https://shannonwu.github.io/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://shannonwu.github.io/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2020, 空山夜语</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[幻想的瘟疫｜精神分析手札]]></title>
        <id>https://shannonwu.github.io/post/delusion of plague-psychoanalst </id>
        <link href="https://shannonwu.github.io/post/delusion of plague-psychoanalst ">
        </link>
        <updated>2020-02-11T23:27:50.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://shannonwu.github.io/post-images/1581464757915.jpeg" alt="" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>当我们在遭遇瘟疫的时候，我们在遭遇什么？2019年12月31日，世界卫生组织驻中国分部向世卫组织提交了一份涉及中国湖北省武汉市出现了不明原因的病毒性肺炎的信息。</p>
<p>##1.瘟疫的心理学</p>
<p>这一部分我们将讨论的是，从公共政策和经济学模型的角度，看瘟疫之下的城市管控的心理学。我们会发现在工作的过程中，有趋利避害的部分。驱力避害的基本工作模式对应这一个基本的欲望动力结构。什么是人群的欲望呢？人类总是遵循着人自身的欲望行动，而当一个组织和团队出现在人们面前，我们也是否可以推演成一种组织心理学的基本结构？欲望总是混沌的欲望，而他总是伴随着团队行动而来。在进行本文城市自救指南的行动指南的书写前，我们意图简单的阐释其基本的心理学原理。这一部分并非指涉瘟疫传播，而是讨论在瘟疫面前的人的行动。为下文中讨论具体到个人的行动指南进行理论论证。</p>
<p>瘟疫是人类古老的伴侣。甚至在人类尚未出现于地球的时代，据古代病理学的研究，疾病与地球上的生命几乎同时出现。因此，疾病也是人类古老的伴侣。如果我们去定义医学，我们或可以用最直白的概念对医学加以描述，“是指自己或者借助于他人以解除痛苦，或修补由外伤或疾病所致的损伤，那么首先便应想到医学起源于人的本能，正如痛苦最初的表现也来自本能一样。”医学也是一门涉及人的学问。在卡斯蒂廖尼的《医学史》中，他写到“但是现代医学事业，不能而且也不应当缺乏与医学的根本，即对病人的精确观察的密切联系，人们现在正对此进行苦苦探索。这几乎全面回到生物学观念和希波克拉底的方法，这即便是不自觉行为，也说明医生在行医治病和周密思考的时候，绝不能完全被试管、显微镜或任何一种人为的教条所束缚。不论个别还是群体的生物体，都是一种时时演进着的生命单位，因此医学本身也一直是在变化的过程中。我们应该承认，世界上并不存在含有绝对正确定义的学说，或能够完全适用于医学某部门的体系。几乎可以说没有一种错误不带有一丝真理，同样也没有一种真理不带有一丝错误，纵然是绝对真理也不例外。”医学总是面向着人，探讨医学，即是涉及到人的内外部结构、社会与团体中的病痛的现象。即便从流行病与传染病学的意义上，疾病的困境不仅涉及的是涉及个体的痛苦，更涉及的是集体的创伤。如果说个体的痛苦是个体的症状，瘟疫乃是社会性的症状。精神分析关心的是症状及其背后的机制，如果我们把一场瘟疫视为作为整体的人类社会的症状，我们即可以通过同构的方式，对瘟疫本身进行分析。<br>
###1.1 作为症状的瘟疫</p>
<p>我们讨论瘟疫的时候，是具体讨论着一个个个案。在近年来的瘟疫中，存留在人们记忆中最深的，还是去年的猪瘟。这一次猪瘟的蔓延，令猪肉价格在2019年度达道了有史以来的新高。这样的畜牧业瘟疫，影响了人们的生活，就在人们即将伴随着再也无法愉快的享受猪肉及其制品的时刻，人们发现在2020年的新春佳节即将到来时，一种就其病原学与症状学属性上极为类同于SARS的疾病正在武汉蔓延。最早有涉及本次疫情的报道是2020年1月2日关于武汉的一则行政处罚条例的新闻，该新闻在央视播出。最早的新闻，是8人因传播“病毒性肺炎”的不实消息而被依法处理。随后而来的新闻中，“武汉华南海鲜市场现不明原因肺炎病人，市场休市整治”这样的新闻，以百态的方式出现在央视的网页中。大概一个月前的中国民众绝对无法想象到，自己的人生将被这样一条简单甚至有些粗糙的新闻彻底改变。</p>
<p>随着2020年春节大年二十九凌晨两点中的一道封城令，武汉全城被封锁。随后而来的是湖北其他城市也逐渐进入封城之中，这个春节注定是中国人心中的集体记忆。所有的新闻都在宣传着提倡取消人们传统形式的拜年与聚会，在乡村地区，有些村口已经开始经由那道曾经响彻了劝阻新型冠状肺炎患者和自武汉归来的人员行动的口号。我们不难发现，这样的现象不仅仅构成了作为症状的传染病的个体症状，而更包含了作为公共卫生事件的瘟疫构成了整个社会有机体的症状。在这样一个症状的背后，我们可以从三个层面对瘟疫作为人类社会</p>
<p>##2.愤怒的传播学</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[哈姆雷特与欲念危机]]></title>
        <id>https://shannonwu.github.io/post/Hamlet and the crisis of desire</id>
        <link href="https://shannonwu.github.io/post/Hamlet and the crisis of desire">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-26T21:55:48.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>节译自Ehsan Azari, <em>Lacan and the Destiny of Literature</em></p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>节译自Ehsan Azari, <em>Lacan and the Destiny of Literature</em></p>
<!-- more -->
<h1 id="哈姆雷特与欲念危机">哈姆雷特与欲念危机</h1>
<p>哈姆雷特与欲念危机</p>
<p>（节译自Ehsan Azari,Lacan and the Destiny of Literature）</p>
<p>Hamlet and the crisis of desire</p>
<p>The tragedy of Hamlet interested Lacan chiefly because of its spectacular structure, Oedipal backdrop, and Shakespeare’s unique poetic skills in dramatizing desire in crisis. Lacan admits this at the outset of his remarks on Hamlet in hisSeminar VI: Le Désir et son Interprétation when he says that the play has ‘[a]n excep- tional power of captivation’ (Lacan, 1977, 11). Lacan’s theory of desire comes into full swing in his criticism of Hamlet and is of special significance for literary studies because, for Lacan, Hamlet was a modern hero caught up in the Other’s desire. This point is cardinal because it answers the question raised by tradi- tional Shakespearean studies about the play: why did Shakespeare subvert the traditional Aristotelian definition of tragedy? From Dr Johnson to Eliot, for many critics the character of Hamlet was a mistake on Shakespeare’s part because he fails to provide a clear-cut reason for Hamlet’s indecision. T. S. Eliot continued such an arguably humanist literary exegetics in expressing difficulty with both Hamlet as a drama and Hamlet as the character in his brief essay on the Shakespearean text. In order to show the significance of Lacan’s sustained criticism of Hamlet for contemporary poststructuralist Shakespearean studies, we will first clarify Eliot’s trouble with Hamlet. T. S. Eliot writes, ‘[s]o far from being Shakespeare’s masterpiece, the play [Hamlet] is most certainly an artistic failure. In several ways the play is puzzling, and disquieting as is none of the others . . . It is the “Mona Lisa” of literature’ (Eliot, 1975, 47). Eliot seems to have trouble with Shakespeare’s subversion of the traditional norms of tragedy and the tragic hero. He highlights the following enigmas in his reading ofHamlet: the neither effect of Hamlet’s mother’s guilt on her son that neither can be expressed, nor does Shakespeare succeed in treating it properly, or artic- ulating the two of them in art; and Hamlet’s emotions and feelings are so intense and excessive that they remain beyond objectification. Such a mental state makes Hamlet ‘[d]oubtless a subject of study for a pathologist’ (49). We can see these statements as the final words of traditional humanist literary criticism of the play. On the other hand, Lacan’s reading of Shakespeare’s text as a drama of desire helps unravel many of the mysteries of Hamlet.</p>
<p>Let us begin with answering the important question: why is Hamlet a tragedy of desire?</p>
<p>Lacan points to a major breakdown in the path of Hamlet’s desire, a break- down through which he ends up lost in a chaotic desire. He doesn’t know how to desire, mainly because his desire is not his own. Instead, he carries Gertrude’s desire as his Other. Hamlet’s total reliance on the Other’s desire brings out an effect of incongruity within the structure of registers, mainly because of an incoherent incorporation of the imaginary and symbolic in his subjectivity. This makes it impossible for him to be integrated successfully into the symbolic reg- ister. In other words, Hamlet’s inability to assimilate his desire beyond the Oedipal triangle into the symbolic is the primary reason for this chaotic desire th-</p>
<p>at Lacan terms the tragedy of desire in Hamlet. Lacan translates Freud’s term for Hamlet, a ‘tragedy of destiny’, into the tragedy of desire. As Freud says in ‘On Hamlet and Oedipus’, Hamlet is a Renaissance immitation of Oedipus Rex. Freud saw the play as an effect of the incompatibility of the will and destiny, as was Sophocles’s play: ‘[i]ts tragic effect is said to lie in the contrast between the supreme will of the gods and the vain attempts of mankind to escape the evil that threatens them’ (Freud, 1970a, 81). In the Lacanian approach, this tragic effect is seen to develop because of the conflict between human desire and the law of the super-ego. This conflict in desire shows itself in Hamlet’s hesitation, procrastination, mourning, indecision, feigned madness and so on that make his self divided between his weak ego, the object of his desire and the Other, the place from where he gets the assurance of his own existence and discourse.</p>
<p>Contrary to Eliot’s assertion, Shakespeare has successfully illustrated the ambiguous state in which Hamlet continuously procrastinates and remains indecisive through unpredictable changes of behaviour. He breaks with Ophe- lia for no reason, an event which shows the rise of an imbalance in his uncon- scious fantasy. Because of this imbalance, Hamlet loses any guarantee of the stability of his desire. This is the moment identified by Lacan as the moment of Hamlet’s depersonalization, when he rejects Ophelia, because from then on she is no longer an object a in relation to Hamlet’s desire. She represents the primal object of desire of which he is deprived in the symbolic. When Hamlet was still in love with Ophelia, her position as an object a in fantasy had offered him a stage on which to play out his desire. Ophelia, from this point on, leaves the stage of fantasy in Hamlet’s desire. We learn of this when Ophelia brings the news of the sudden change in Hamlet’s behaviour to Polonius. This sudden change means for Lacan a subjective rupture that is caused by a disparity between the components of fantasy, the barred subject and the object a. This shift also triggers an outcome that reveals a pathological crossover from uncon- scious thought into a conscious message. Lacan further observes that because of such a disparity, Freud conceptualized the Unheimlich (uncanny), a moment in which the imaginary limit between the subject and the object changes. This sudden change freezes the subject and something that was hidden from him becomes visible. Ophelia discloses this irruption in Hamlet that changes him from what she has earlier described as ‘the glass of fashion’, and ‘mould of form’, into someone who has just emerged from ‘hell’:</p>
<p>My lord, as I was sewing in my chamber,</p>
<p>Lord Hamlet, with his doublet all unbraced,</p>
<p>No hat upon his head, his stockings fouled,</p>
<p>Ungartered, and down-gyvèd to his ankle,</p>
<p>Pale as his shirt, his knees knocking each other,</p>
<p>And with a look so piteous in purport</p>
<p>As if he had been loosed out of hell</p>
<p>To speak of horrors, he comes before me.</p>
<p>(H, II, i, 87–94)</p>
<p>This uncanny irruption in Hamlet once again reveals itself in the graveyard scene, where the dead Ophelia, the abandoned object, becomes a fetishized object of his desire. Hamlet shows his passionate love for the dead Ophelia, an object that he cannot have any more. This produces ‘[a] reintegration of the object a, won back here at the price of mourning and death’ (Lacan, 1977, 24). This restoration of the object brings Hamlet’s desire to boiling point and causes him to jump into her tomb in order to prevent his rival, Laertes, from grabbing the symbolic phallus. When she is loved, she is an object a, and when dead in a tomb she represents the empty space, the dead body, and the lack of the phallus. Such moments, in which rivalry, aggression and ambivalence towards the idealized object take place, are repeated several times in the play. The fenc- ing scene, for example, upsets the balance in desire when the resurgence of the imaginary into the symbolic register takes place, changing Hamlet from an indecisive posture into an aggressive stance of action. In such instances, as Lacan puts it, ‘[t]he playwright situates the basis of aggressivity in this paroxysm of absorption in the imaginary register, formally expressed as a mirror relation- ship, a mirrored reaction’ (31). In the graveyard scene, an imaginary inscription of desire emerges in the symbolic, and the ghost in the play represents the emergence of the real in the symbolic. Lacan sees the symptomatic aspect of Hamlet’s desire in this imbalance that is inscribed in the play in a series of bizarre actions. The real cuts through the symbolic in terms of uncanny and bizarre in this play, for it as we often insist are inassimilable in the symbolic. Lacan observes Hamlet’s dragging of Polonius’ body, the hiding of the corpse and the graveyard on the stage as among the gaps in the real that emerge uncensored in Shakespeare’s play. The gap in the real and consequently in the existence of the subject, as Lacan emphasizes, cannot be articulated in the sig- nifying chain because of the limit of language in homogenizing the real. These gaps locate Hamlet and his desire in what Lacan calls ‘the blackout of signifiers’ (49). This blackout or syncope means that when an act or gesture doesn’t lend itself to signification, it emerges in the real. This is a situation of a total loss where the function of speech – the symbolic exchange and the function of love – transference – all fail. This means that the configuration of the Oedipal love-bond fails to cross over to the symbolic bond of love. Desire of man is indeed hell as Lacan said in response to a question by Marcel Ritter (Marini, 1992, 243). This hell is where Hamlet turns into a ‘coward’, a natural result of a chaotic desire, as Lacan writes, ‘[d]esire, what is called desire, suffices to make life meaningless if it turns someone into a coward’ (Lacan, 2006, 661).</p>
<p>如果你喜欢我的翻译，欢迎您找我聊聊精神分析：</p>
<p>微信号:wjwu1990</p>
<p>Q Q 号:416678343</p>
<p>手机号:13870688223</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[第五章 莎士比亚戏剧中的欲念]]></title>
        <id>https://shannonwu.github.io/post/Chapter 5 Shakespeare’s Theatre of Desire</id>
        <link href="https://shannonwu.github.io/post/Chapter 5 Shakespeare’s Theatre of Desire">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-26T19:17:31.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>节译自Ehsan Azari, <em>Lacan and the Destiny of Literature</em></p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>节译自Ehsan Azari, <em>Lacan and the Destiny of Literature</em></p>
<!-- more -->
<h1 id="第五章-莎士比亚戏剧中的欲念">第五章 莎士比亚戏剧中的欲念</h1>
<p><strong>Chapter 5  Shakespeare’s Theatre of Desire</strong></p>
<p>From our theoretical inquiry into desire as well as our exploration of Lacan’s modes of reading literature and critical methodologies in the previous chapters, we are now able to examine desire in Shakespeare. This chapter is divided into two parts in order to investigate the structure and textual modes of both masculine and feminine desires in a selection of key Shakespearean texts. In light of Lacan’s seminar on Hamlet, the first part will scrutinize the literary articulation of masculine desire in that play, with special focus on some of Lacan’s important theoretical points that have been mostly omitted in post- Lacanian literary debates.</p>
<p>从我们在先前章节中对于欲念的理论性探索，与拉康式的文学解读与批评方法论的研究，我们现在即可检视莎士比亚文本中的欲念。本章分为两部分，以探讨选定的莎士比亚文本中男性与女性欲念的结构和文本图式。本章分为两部分，以探讨选定的莎士比亚文本中男性与女性欲念的结构和文本图式。受拉康讨论班《哈姆莱特》启发，第一部分将细查的是该剧本中男性欲念的文学链接，主要针对的是那些被后拉康文论讨论所忽略的理论要点。</p>
<p>I wish to consider those important points that make this play the epitome of a masculine desire in deep crisis. This crisis will be followed by a reading of Hamlet’s soliloquies – a metonymical vehicle for sustaining the mourning that is constitutive of his desire. Then we will explain Hamlet’s interpersonal swing between the object in and of desire, the theme of the hour of the Other, and Hamlet’s conversation with Gertrude, as the dénoue- ment of a chaotic desire. This section ends with a study of the play-within-the-play, Hamlet’s ‘mouse trap’, not as a traditionally Oedipal allegory, but as textual evidence for the return of Hamlet’s desire. In the second part of the chapter, the focus will be on paradigms of feminine desire in Coriolanus, Macbeth and The Merchant of Venice. The latter texts will allow us to demonstrate the multiplicity of feminine desire, and the interdependence of masculine and feminine desires not as two opposite categories but as two types of unconscious preference. We will examine two kinds of the phallic mother in Coriolanus and Macbeth. We will conclude with a survey of the fluidity of feminine desire in The Merchant of Venice.</p>
<p>我希望能考察那些促使这个剧本成为男性欲望深度危机的典型的要点。这些危机随着对于哈姆雷特独白的阅读而来——一种换喻性手段以绵延其欲望基础的哀悼。随后，我们将阐释哈姆雷特人际间针对客体中和客体自身的欲念的延宕；彼者时间的主题；作为混沌欲念的结局，哈姆雷特与乔特鲁德的对话。这一部分以针对剧中剧——哈姆雷特的《捕鼠器》——的研究收尾，它并不是传统意义上的俄狄浦斯隐喻，而是作为哈姆雷特的欲念回归的文本证据。本章的第二部分将关注在《科利奥兰纳斯》、《麦克白》和《威尼斯商人》中的女性欲望图式。接下来的文本将允许我们演示女性欲望的多重性，进而说明男性与女性欲望的依存性，并不是两种对立的类别，而是两种无意识的倾向。我们将检视在《科利奥兰纳斯》和《麦克白》中的石祖母亲。我们将以《威尼斯商人》中女性欲望的流动性报告作结。</p>
<p>These plays are selected because: first, they offer a fertile ground for Lacan’s theory of desire in which literary experience converges on psychoanalytic experiment; and second, some of the texts display prototypes and models of theoretical material that Lacan was to develop later. This also reveals that Lacan seems always keen to see Hamlet like any other literary text, representing a pre-existing truth about desire. From this vantage point, Lacan and Shakespeare make an ideal match, as the former postulates a psychoanalytic theoretical position for which the second has already produced textual illustrations.</p>
<p>这些剧本之所以入选，是因为：一来，他们为拉康的欲望理论在文学与精神分析经验的交汇提供了肥沃的土壤；二来，其中部分文本展示了拉康晚期创造的基础模型与图示的理论材料。这些文本也揭示了拉康相较于其他文本对哈姆雷特的偏爱，再现了关涉欲望的既存真理。正是在这样的有利地位上，拉康与莎士比亚构成一对理想组合，前者假设为精神分析的理论地点，为后者制造了文本说明。</p>
<p><strong>如果你喜欢我的翻译，欢迎您找我聊聊精神分析：</strong></p>
<p><strong>微信号:wjwu1990 Q Q 号:416678343 手机号:13870688223</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://gen.lib.rus.ec/book/index.php?md5=66A52958383FFE862F493E9FA7363DF1">原文链接</a></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[精神分析文献翻译重启]]></title>
        <id>https://shannonwu.github.io/post/chongqifanyi</id>
        <link href="https://shannonwu.github.io/post/chongqifanyi">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-26T17:32:56.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>废柴也得有废柴的活法，比如自言自语的翻译...</p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>废柴也得有废柴的活法，比如自言自语的翻译...</p>
<!-- more -->
<p>我这个人无话可说，也不喜欢做什么高深语。因此也写不出什么论文，大致上总归是个傻子。对于自己不懂不明白的现象，也不喜欢发什么高论，和高人相处久了，就变得越来越无话可说。别人说得比我好、写得比我好、我说什么都像傻子。不过看多了、读多了高人的文章，就想着把高人们的观点慢慢介绍给大家。于是就起心动念做点简单的翻译。也算是胁迫着自己再去读书复习，一方面堵住自己瓜燥不安的嘴，另一方面，也赌上那些瓜燥不安人自以为是的嘴吧。</p>
<p>不过这个计划其实很早就有，最近才下定心思做起来。以前读书的时候就觉得自己其实没啥想法，主要是喜欢看别人的文章，做一点推荐介绍工作。我这种笨蛋能做的，其实也就是把高人们的观点翻译成中国话，把洋人说的明白、想得透彻的事情让大家知道。无话可说的自己，也能说点“吴话”。</p>
<p>每次向人提起自己的硕士专业，文艺学，就像是傻子见学霸一样，有一种萌萌地自卑感。和一圈专业精神分析牛人比起来自己就很鸡贼了。我这个人不喜欢说自己都弄不明白的事情，最反感的也是滥竽充数。于是乎，这个多少还能和文字打点交道的傻子，唯一能做的，也就是像只老牛一样，把自觉好的文章翻译给大家。</p>
<p>当时王亮问我，你翻译以后又没法出版。我想一想，其实也就不为了出版，就是为了让我这种无话可说的废柴能多少多少说出点什么。毕竟和牛逼烘烘的高人比起来，我不是什么牛逼学校毕业的，更没啥牛逼烘烘的家学，更不是什么牛逼烘烘的导师带出来的学生。除去自己常年对心理学的兴趣之外，没啥专业文凭，和那些留法博士、川大硕士、中科院博士不是一回事。作为一个长期以此为耻的中文系吃饭生，能做的也就是做点翻译趴。</p>
<p>另外，我这个人读书太快，又不喜欢做笔记，唯有做翻译才会把自己消磨空一点，也算是对自己生活工作负责的态度趴。就这样！废柴也得有废柴的活法，比如自言自语的翻译...</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[作家之为责任｜吴老师的文学课]]></title>
        <id>https://shannonwu.github.io/post/writer&apos;s duty</id>
        <link href="https://shannonwu.github.io/post/writer&apos;s duty">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-15T21:37:11.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>做个写作者来提笔写作带给人自由的感受，写作使你得以履行自己的职责。作家之为责任，正是通过最简单的形态，传递神的讯息。</strong></p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>做个写作者来提笔写作带给人自由的感受，写作使你得以履行自己的职责。作家之为责任，正是通过最简单的形态，传递神的讯息。</strong></p>
<!-- more -->
<p>在娜塔莉·戈德堡的《再活一次：用写作来调心》中，娜塔莉写下了这样的句子“做个写作者来提笔写作带给人自由的感受，写作使你得以履行自己的职责。我原本意味自由代表着为所欲为。自由其实意味着知道自己是谁，在这个世上应当做些什么，然后确实地去完成自己的责任；自由并不是叫你转移目标，想着自己不应当再写你的犹太家人。然而，在一切灰飞烟灭前，记录下移居美国的那些第一代戈德堡家人的历史，记录他们当年在布鲁克林、长岛、迈阿密海滩的往事，就是你该扮演的生命角色。”是的，作家之为责任、文学之为责任，正是在写作本身。正如同在《九个人》中，张新颖写到沈从文：</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“沈从文凭借自己的生命经验、体悟和真切的感情，追问什么是“真的历史”，“一本历史书除了告我诉讼们些另一时代最笨的人相斫相杀以外有些什么？”这个强烈的感受，恰恰呼应了梁启超对旧史学的批判，连蚊子意象多是不约而同：“昔人谓《左传》为相斫书。岂惟《左传》，若二十四史，真可谓地球上空前绝后之一大相斫书也。而沈从文心智所系，是在这样的历史书写传统之外、被疏忽了若干年代的更广大的平凡人群。在文学写作中，沈从文把满腔的文学热情投射到了绵延如长河的普通人生死哀乐上...”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>在中国文学传统中，与史传文学对举的，即是诗歌的传统，如果恰如梁启超所言，史传文学全然是一幅“相斫”的历史，那么诗歌便是所有能书写、能歌唱者的历史，它浸润着文学的责任，即把那些被宏大历史事件遮蔽下的真实感受展现在人们面前，即它就是“有情”的历史。因此，我们说文学的责任与历史事件相去并不遥远，有形的历史总是呈现着关于具体事件、行动和过往的具象形态，而文学总归是谈论着我们自身的经验，那些呈现着经验的文学往往赤裸着把真相不戴面具般的呈报在我们面前。文学的责任也正是在记录和补充那些被遗忘的过往，而这些过去的故事标定了我们自身的位置，并为我们的行动提供坐标。</p>
<p>这些日子，接受了长期的精神分析的工作之后，我忽然失去了关于自己行动的方向标，尤其是受到自己分析家的宗教信仰的影响以后，我对于自己是谁、将去往何方更是充满了不确定。而这种不确定带来的是行动的无目标性，昨天晚上和老友L聊天时，他倒是一阵见血的指出，“你这是失去了行动的方向了。”是的，做分析之后很多很多的欲望从身体中涌现出来，可是每一个欲望都如此真实、如此真切，但内心总归有一种声音在呼唤我回到文学、回到故事中。就在我即将前往龙虎山接受传度前，端午节的这几天我又以逛书店的方式放松，拾得书屋的午后充满了阿蒙和警长的气味，他们就像是两只可爱的毛球一般在书店里做了镇宅神兽。我忽然发现了几年前一直想读的张新颖写的《沈从文的前半生》和《沈从文的后半生》。只记得把遗留在书店的书籍带走，忘记了买走这两本书。等我回家以后，忽然想起这两本书曾经常居在我的近代史阅读书目中时，我想是时候开始重新回到过去时代的文学现场中了，或许也是时机到来。作为写作者的我读到张新颖写沈从文，又何尝不是“与吾心有戚戚焉”。于是我忽然想起了自己曾经在中文系边缘游荡的日子里，是怎样和朋友们大声的争执诗歌的多种理解方式，又是怎样在读过科塔萨尔之后缓解了内心的焦灼。文学对我而言是最好的抑郁症治疗药，只要手里拿着本小说，我的内心就充满了宁静。因此，这份文学的光芒变成了文学的责任，在我有生之年，指引了前行的道路。</p>
<p>曾经有一起接受分析的朋友问我，是精神分析拯救了我嘛？我想不是，我最初痛苦的部分正是自己失去了写作力量，从而希望借助精神分析能重新寻找回这份力量，当我迷失在道教实修的丛林中时，我已经彻底忘记了我进入精神分析的最初动机，那个关于职业的预言性的判断，总是在影响着我关于自己的前路的选择，可是我的内心总是这样说着自己“你可以逃避一生、通过这种各样的方式逃避写作、通过修道逃避、通过瑜伽、塔罗、占星、术数、考博，但写作的责任不正是通过双手来创造嘛？”失去写作的能力的时刻，到底是失去了写下诗句的时刻，正是通过写作，我逃避自杀的宿命，而这份活着的信念却也成为了阻碍自己写作的力量。我们总归是时间中的一部分，我们总要灰飞烟灭，写作无法阻止死亡到来，但却可以让我们重新明白时间本身，他总是在流经身体的各个角落，记录着关于痛苦、哀伤、欢愉和时光的瞬间。是的，这些曾经的记忆就是我们的责任、去记录自身。写作，它只是一个动词，但在这动词的背后，却透射着生命全部的呼喊。从生命中迸发的不仅有你全部的创造力，还有爱，一份自身的礼物。总有什么令我们活着，我想对我而言，能令我接纳卑微的生命、微薄的工资、烦恼的现实的，大概就是文学，去写作、去谈论、去分享，这就是令我卑微的活着的东西，那些过往的记忆凝结成一条关于自身的传说，在时间中穿行。</p>
<p>原文是关于沈从文的演讲，在全文之末，张新颖“说”到：</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“时间绵延不绝，个体生命从头到尾，在时间的长河中不过是一瞬；但是，一些伟大的个体，却能奋力凿通自己生命的头和尾，既向前延伸也向后延伸，他从在他之前的过去时间里源源不断汲取丰富和支持自己的力量，他把自己的一切安排、托付给在他之后的未来时间。</p>
<p>站在今天的位置，我们会发现，时间的故事，大跨度地计量时间，一代一代地计量时间的故事，最终是一个时间胜利的故事。”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>我的分析家曾经问过我这样一个问题，我一时不曾给出确定的答案：“你为什么会对那些文学研究者移情那么深？”我想，到了今天，读到了张新颖的文字，我忽然知道了这个问题的答案：</p>
<p><strong>因为，对我而言，文学是我能忍受着生命的痛苦、挨过所有的伤痕、接纳世界的不幸的方式。正是在写作和谈论文学中，我忽然记忆起自己的全部过往，是那些动人的故事打动了我的心灵。个体的人是有限的，但是在作家的心灵中，万物与我同在，正是在这些个体化的痛苦中，万物的创伤与我共舞，在书写自己的伤痕时，作家也从每一个人的经验中，传递出永恒的疗愈之光。试想，如果没有乔伊斯，拉康能创造出他后期涉及精神病临床工作的重要结构和分析结束的重要标志吗？如果不去阅读乔伊斯，我们终究不会明白圣状的意义，不会明白在潘果夫的临床工作和荣格学派设计的沙盘游戏中，为什么双手能创造出意识深处的真相。胶泥的意义、艺术治疗的意义、书写与阅读治疗的意义、以及后现代叙事治疗的意义正是通过那些伟大的作家工作。如果没有莎士比亚，弗洛伊德能创造出他的俄狄浦斯情结吗？正如同哈罗德·布鲁姆所言，我们每个人都被莎士比亚所限定，而中国人呢？我们难道不是被红楼梦、西厢记、西游记、庄子、论语、易经所限定吗？难道我们能在不谈论沈从文的时候了解我们自己吗？一个人是如何的狂妄才敢认为我们不是这些伟大心灵的学生？也正是在这样的意义上说，精神分析的根本总归需要回到文学而不是道教实修中，如果没有那个讲述道教故事的人，又何来道教？我想我宁愿做一个没有个性、没有立场、没有选择的人，来承载万有传递的讯息！一个道士又是一种固定的身份，而这样的身份却不是一条优质的通道？赫尔墨斯的神使总是透过最质朴的故事传递讯息，那些最隐晦的真相，总是置身在最简单的形态中。正是因此，我回到文学，去履行我的责任，面对我自己的人生，即便你不再有我需要的答案，我的人生也需要我自己去以死相抵、活下去。写作，直到生命自然终结的那一天、谈论文学、直到自然枯萎的时刻。作家之为责任，正是通过最简单的形态，传递神的讯息。</strong></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[姜余：《儿童精神分析五讲》札记Ⅰ]]></title>
        <id>https://shannonwu.github.io/post/children-psychoanalysis Ⅰ</id>
        <link href="https://shannonwu.github.io/post/children-psychoanalysis Ⅰ">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-06-15T20:07:17.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>【吴按】经过这将近两个月的自我定位，我还是决定继续我的精神分析工作，由此，我也想正好逮住我自己终于把自己的人生想清楚以后开始写涉及我自己一直很关注的精神分析和儿童之间的相关主题的札记。这些含混不明的手记正如同我们在分析中体验的那样充满歧义、含混和不确定。因此，希望读者们能开始渐渐体验这种在文本中的不确定性、非大学辞说和反主人辞说性。</p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>【吴按】经过这将近两个月的自我定位，我还是决定继续我的精神分析工作，由此，我也想正好逮住我自己终于把自己的人生想清楚以后开始写涉及我自己一直很关注的精神分析和儿童之间的相关主题的札记。这些含混不明的手记正如同我们在分析中体验的那样充满歧义、含混和不确定。因此，希望读者们能开始渐渐体验这种在文本中的不确定性、非大学辞说和反主人辞说性。</p>
<!-- more -->
<h1 id="01">01</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>给孩子做分析，是个有趣的冒险。</p>
</blockquote>
<p>当迪迪耶这样描述的时候，我会联想起我自己做分析时常常体验到的我自己的冒险感，这种冒险感是逐渐远离生活的确定性、平稳的，而充满了生命的活力、差异性和搞怪性。由此，我能明显地体验到我周围朋友圈的变化以及与家人关系之间的张力的逐渐消失。所以，我认为，对于所有有幸进入精神分析的朋友，都因这样的缘分体验到了活生生的生活，酸甜苦辣尽收其中。对成年人来说尚充满张力的分析，孩子的心灵更加敏锐，因此他们更容易敏感的体验到周遭的变化。尤其是当我们阅读迪迪耶先生的小分析者们的种种行动时，我想作为成年人的我甚至认为不如他们。他们的坚毅、勇敢和无畏，以及创造力种种，都令人钦佩，精神分析家们终生是孩子们的学生，因他们身上未被大学辞说所淹没的部分正是成年人们如饥似渴的想象力。因此，我邀请每一位愿意进入孩子的心灵的人们都去看看你们的人生，是不是充满了平庸的陈词滥调、满足于被自己的一己知见捆绑的人生？或许，这正是时候向孩子们学习！</p>
<h1 id="02">02</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>米歇尔·吉布尔是这样的人，他能以一种动人心魄的方式，见证人生当中一些至关重要的相遇，并以此和精神分析及话语建立起联系。他毫无保留地谈论那些彻底改变他的经历。不管怎样，一次分析就是一次相遇。</p>
</blockquote>
<p>我想，每一个接收过精神分析的朋友都不应该忘记吉布尔先生。如果没有吉布尔先生在霍大同先生尚在学生时代以几乎无报酬的方式接待了霍先生，我们今天深受精神分析号召的人又怎样有机缘亲身实证精神分析的妙处，又如何以在临床工作中的个人体验作为生活的起点，重构我们自身的人生？正吉布尔和霍大同先生的遭遇，才带来的这一切。这是法国式精神分析得以在中国传播的契机。之前豆瓣上有人问我是不是霍先生的学生，我想这个问题问得十分微妙。严格意义上，我们都是霍先生的学生，因为霍先生十年如一日坚持开展开放式网络+地面讨论班，所有精神分析中心成员都听过他的课。而今日以拉康精神分析为旗帜的分析家无论是直系交手或是隔代遗传的方式，精神分析在中国临床中的影响和传递中，霍先生无论如何都是重要一环。而吉布尔先生正是所有中国精神分析传递者的最初因缘，正是因此，我想在此表达一份谢意与敬意！确实如此，精神分析正是这样一种遭际，它令每一个进入精神分析的人和自我奇异的遭遇着，并充分地释放着天地间的能量，每一个神秘的因缘最终把精神分析带给了他们需要的人！</p>
<h1 id="03">03</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>我再给大家举个例子，以见其人美德。一天，在一次精神分析师的会议上，一个喝得醉醺醺的流浪汉满身酒气地闯了进来，大声嚷嚷着，破坏了会场的秩序。为了继续会议，其他分析师都想这个闯进来的流浪汉出去。但米歇尔·吉布尔却非常自然地走到那位醉汉跟前，建议他到讲台上讲讲他刚刚说过的话。说完，吉布尔回到座位，倾听下面的会议议题。</p>
<p>流浪汉果然登上了讲台，说了一通他要说的话。当然，人们什么也没有听懂。待他说完，米歇尔·吉布尔建议他坐下倾听分析师们的发言。事情就这样化解了。</p>
<p>你们会注意到，对于我们这些精神分析师来说，来了局外人，我们就想把他赶到门外，这不是件光彩的事情。因为，在私人场所，为了治疗我们会接触到各种奇怪的人和事。另就社会阶层而言，精神分析师也并不比其他阶层人士更重要。而令人感慨的是，分析师们接触更多的经常是生活优越的人而不是生活困顿的人。</p>
</blockquote>
<p>这一段的感触，恐怕是我对精神分析师肃然起敬、并想终身以此为天职的原动力。我记得听到这个故事并不是在这本书中，而是通过一起做精神分析中的伙伴之口。当我知道吉布尔先生曾经以这样的态度面对周遭的一切时，我才意识到自己当时从高校里出来、选择以精神分析作为自己安身立面之根本的决定是对于自己此生中的重要一环。也因此构成了我此后很多选择的根基。很多朋友关注我，问我没考上博士难不难受？我想相比于精神分析、我的来访和我此生的道路，那个博士学位简直无足轻重，它仅仅是一种标记物、一种广告。个体的荣誉和世间万物比起来，自己确实如此的无足轻重，无所必要的为荣誉、名利、声望以及一切虚无的欲望而奋斗，我累了。因此，吉布尔先生传递出的精神分析正是我对于我自身生命状态的认同。倾听万物，以温柔相待。</p>
<p>前些天在等待的一批张新颖的书一直没有到家里，半夜醒来查看发货进度，却意外地取消了订单。我问自己，还想继续做个不断言说的人吗？还想继续做那些自己都认为对自己而言并不重要却看上去光鲜亮丽的研究吗？是的，那些现当代文学很重要，只是，站在我自己的价值观中，相比于已经幻化成书籍的物件，一个鲜活的、等待倾听的人而言，则更为重要。因人的创造力乃是其根源。换做曾经的我，大概会坚持再下单买一套，可是书真的有那么重要吗？</p>
<p>这个世界不缺乏那些把世界拒之门外的人，人们大声的呼喊、不断地言说、乃至歌唱、乃至疯狂，无不是因为这个世界上缺乏人真正愿意静下心来，倾听他者的声音？很多人说中国文论、中国文学、中国科研的失语（这是很多年以前的说法，不知道现在还能不能提），可是，问题的关键难道不是我们自己都不肯倾听他人的声音吗？精神分析，正是倾听的艺术，是倾听万物的艺术，是宁静而沉静的倾听与回应的艺术。暴力无法改变人心，但倾听可以，我想这就是我对于甘地、室利·阿罗频多、泰戈尔充满敬意，对印度这个古老文明充满敬意的原因。当一个人在受难时，他并不期待着回击、并不以被攻击的同样的方式加以反抗，他们澄净地以宁静地抵抗这个世界强加于其身上的痛苦，这份宁静的力量，则超越于这个世界上所有的辞说，在沉静的大地面前，所有的言说都显现出其失效的部分。我想这就是我看待精神分析和人生的根本性态度，以宁静的倾听，涵容万物。我常常会陷入悖论中，我所憎恨的，最终却以最深的方式拯救我。或许我们所恨的，正是我们一度曾经迷恋的。也正是这索求，令生命陷入无止境的徒劳与苦役中。人生的苦役还将绵延，但那份宁静的倾听之力却不会终结，因它终将通向人生的终结处，并绵延亘古。</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>